NARRATOR: If European imports
like horses and cattle
forever changed the Americas,
American exports to Europe would
forever change life there.
The humble potato is
one important example.
It was grown by peoples of the
Andes for hundreds of years
before the Spaniards arrived.
Once in Europe,
this nutritious vegetable
became the food of the poor,
and it supported a sharp increase
in the European population
beginning in the 1600s.
Ireland’s population grew
more than eightfold.
For many, meals consisted of
potatoes and nothing else.
But then another import
from the Americas arrived:
a deadly fungus.
By the summer of 1845,
potato fields stricken by this
fungus blackened overnight.
The Irish potato famine had begun.
Those who had lived by the
potato now died without it.
Perhaps a million Irish starved to death.
A million others took to
ships headed westward
across the Atlantic.
They became part of perhaps
the most significant cargo
to move between the continents:
the massive wave of people
who would cross the oceans
to start a new life in the Americas.